<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
    <?properties open_access?>
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22870945</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC3519711</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2458-12-618</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-618</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Legionella on board trains: effectiveness of environmental
                    surveillance and decontamination</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Quaranta</surname>
                        <given-names>Gianluigi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>gianluigi.quaranta@rm.unicatt.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A2">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Vincenti</surname>
                        <given-names>Sara</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>sara.vincenti@rm.unicatt.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ferriero</surname>
                        <given-names>Anna Maria</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>annamariaferriero@hotmail.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Boninti</surname>
                        <given-names>Federica</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>bfede77@hotmail.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Sezzatini</surname>
                        <given-names>Romina</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>rominasez@libero.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Turnaturi</surname>
                        <given-names>Cinzia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>cincin60@tiscali.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Gliubizzi</surname>
                        <given-names>Maria Daniela</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>dani_gliu@hotmail.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Munaf&#x000f2;</surname>
                        <given-names>Elio</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
                    <email>elio.munafo@gmail.com</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ceccarelli</surname>
                        <given-names>Gianluca</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
                    <email>Gi.ceccarelli@rfi.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Causarano</surname>
                        <given-names>Carmelo</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
                    <email>c.causarano@rfi.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A11">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Accorsi</surname>
                        <given-names>Massimo</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
                    <email>m.accorsi@rfi.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A12">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Del Nord</surname>
                        <given-names>Pasquale</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
                    <email>p.delnord@rfi.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A13">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ricciardi</surname>
                        <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>wricciardi@rm.unicatt.it</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A14">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Laurenti</surname>
                        <given-names>Patrizia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
                    <email>plaurenti@rm.unicatt.it</email>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institute of Hygiene, Universit&#x000e0; Cattolica del
                Sacro Cuore, L.go F. Vito 1, 00168, Rome, Italy</aff>
            <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>RFI (Italian Railway) Health Service, Via F. A. Pigafetta
                3, 00154, Rome, Italy</aff>
            <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Trenitalia Environmental Work Quality and Safety, Via F. A.
                Pigafetta 3, 00154, Rome, Italy</aff>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>7</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <fpage>618</fpage>
            <lpage>618</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2012 Quaranta et al.; licensee BioMed
                    Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Quaranta et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access"
                    xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
                    <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
                        Creative Commons Attribution License ( <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
                        http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits
                        unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
                        original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/12/618" />
            <abstract>
                <sec>
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p><italic>Legionella pneumophila</italic> is increasingly recognised as a
                        significant cause of sporadic and epidemic community-acquired and nosocomial
                        pneumonia. Many studies describe the frequency and severity of <italic>
                        Legionella</italic> spp. contamination in spa pools, natural pools, hotels
                        and ships, but there is no study analysing the environmental monitoring of <italic>
                        Legionella</italic> on board trains. The aims of the present study were to
                        conduct periodic and precise environmental surveillance of <italic>
                        Legionella</italic> spp. in water systems and water tanks that supply the
                        toilet systems on trains, to assess the degree of contamination of such
                        structures and to determine the effectiveness of decontamination.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Methods</title>
                    <p>A comparative pre-post ecological study was conducted from September 2006 to
                        January 2011. A total of 1,245 water samples were collected from plumbing
                        and toilet water tanks on passenger trains. The prevalence proportion of all
                        positive samples was calculated. The unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test was
                        performed to evaluate statistically significant differences between the mean
                        load values before and after the decontamination procedures; statistical
                        significance was set at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Results</title>
                    <p>In the pre-decontamination period, 58% of the water samples were positive for <italic>
                        Legionella</italic>. Only <italic>Legionella pneumophila</italic> was
                        identified: 55.84% were serogroup 1, 19.03% were serogroups 2&#x02013;14 and
                        25.13% contained both serogroups. The mean bacterial load value was
                        2.14&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;CFU/L. During the
                        post-decontamination period, 42.75% of water samples were positive for <italic>
                        Legionella</italic> spp.; 98.76% were positive for <italic>Legionella
                        pneumophila</italic>: 74.06% contained serogroup 1, 16.32% contained
                        serogroups 2&#x02013;14 and 9.62% contained both. The mean bacterial load in
                        the post-decontamination period was 1.72&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;CFU/L.
                        According to the <italic>t</italic>-test, there was a statistically
                        significant decrease in total bacterial load until approximately one and a
                        half year after beginning the decontamination programme (<italic>p</italic>
                        &#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0097).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Conclusions</title>
                    <p>This study indicates that systematic environmental surveillance could be a
                        useful approach for assessing the risk of exposure to <italic>Legionella</italic>
                        bacteria, which still represents a public health threat. According to the
                        study results, an environmental surveillance programme, followed by
                        decontamination procedures where necessary, would decrease the total
                        bacterial count, protecting the health of travellers and workers.</p>
                </sec>
            </abstract>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec>
            <title>Background</title>
            <p><italic>Legionella pneumophila</italic> is increasingly recognized as a significant
                cause of sporadic and epidemic community-acquired and nosocomial pneumonia.</p>
            <p>In recent years, our understanding of Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease (LD) has improved
                substantially and new diagnostic and treatment strategies have been introduced [<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
            <p>To share knowledge and monitor trends of LD across Europe, the European Working Group
                for <italic>Legionella</italic> Infections (EWGLI) was established in 1986 to better
                protect the health of travellers by improving the detection and control of infection
                sources in European countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
            <p>Members of EWGLI established a European surveillance scheme for travel-associated
                infections in 1987; this surveillance scheme, named EWGLINET in 2002, is the
                EU&#x02019;s surveillance network dedicated to collecting data on cases of LD in the
                EU, including travel-associated LD (TALD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
            <p>Since April 2010, the programme has also been coordinated by European Centre for
                Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC), and the name of the scheme has changed to the
                European Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease Surveillance Network (ELDSNet) [<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
            <p>In the beginning of July 2002, the European Guidelines for Control and Prevention of
                Travel Associated LD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] were introduced in an
                attempt to standardise the investigation of clusters in EWGLINET countries and their
                Ministers of Health were asked to support the use of these guidelines.</p>
            <p>In 2009, the EWGLINET surveillance scheme reported a total of 818 cases (794
                confirmed and 24 presumptive) of travel-associated LD with onset of illness, which
                is a decrease of 52 cases compared with 2008 and is 129 fewer than in 2007. The
                countries that reported the most cases by country of residence were the UK
                (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;173), Italy (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;169) and the Netherlands
                (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;109). These three countries have consistently reported the
                greatest number of cases to EWGLINET for several years [<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
            <p>The Italian National Surveillance System has reported that, in Italy, the incidence
                of Legionellosis has been increasing in the last ten years despite a slightly
                decreasing number of notified cases in the time periods from 2002&#x02013;2004 and
                2005&#x02013;2006. In 2009, 1,200 cases of Legionellosis were diagnosed and reported
                (1,146 confirmed and 54 presumptive), with an incidence proportion of twenty cases
                per million (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="B6">6</xref>].</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Cases of Legionellosis notified in Italy, 2000&#x02013;2009 (Data source:
                        Italian Ministry of Health).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="1471-2458-12-618-1" />
            </fig>
            <p>In Italy, in 2009, a total of 281 TALD cases, including both Italian and foreign
                tourists, were reported to the National Health Institute [<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="B6">6</xref>]. Among these, 178 cases of legionellosis concern to Italian
                Tourists. The 86% of them stayed at the hotels, the 5.6% stayed at camping and the
                8,4% in other structures. The 10% of 178 cases have travelled in foreign locations.</p>
            <p>Many studies describe the frequency and strength of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp.
                contamination in spa pools, natural pools, hotels and ships [<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], but no study has
                been conducted that addresses the environmental monitoring of <italic>Legionella</italic>
                on board trains.</p>
            <p>To protect the health of travellers and workers, the Health Service of Italian
                Railways and the Hygiene Institute of the Catholic University in Rome established
                for the first time an environmental surveillance programme to evaluate the degree of
                contamination on trains and the effectiveness and length of water tank
                decontamination.</p>
            <p>We have examined air conditioning plants and toilet water tanks, which are the
                primary sources of biological agents. The air conditioning plants on board
                Trenitalia trains are planned and built to avoid condensed water stagnation. Water
                is directly drained out of the trains by canalisations that prevent microorganism
                proliferation. Passenger trains contain water tanks made of steel or resin that
                supply hygienic services by falling water and they may have a varied capacity (from
                200 to 1,800 litres) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>A comparative pre-post ecological study was conducted from September 2006 to January
                2011.</p>
            <sec>
                <title>Water sampling and microbiological analysis</title>
                <p>Plumbing and toilet water tanks on passenger trains were examined.</p>
                <p>Two samples were collected from every sampling site at a single time point: one
                    sample was harvested immediately after the tap was switched on and without
                    flaming for qualitative evaluation of the <italic>Legionella</italic> species
                    and serogroup and the second sample was collected for quantitative determination
                    (<italic>Legionella</italic> CFU/L of water) after the water ran for at least
                    5&#x02013;10 minutes, which is more representative of the water flowing in the
                    system. At least 6 to 12 water samples were collected weekly.</p>
                <p>One litre of water was collected in sterile bottles with 0.01% sodium
                    thiosulphate to neutralise any residual chlorine; water samples were transported
                    in a suitable cool box, protected from direct light and processed within four
                    hours after collection.</p>
                <p>Microbiological detection of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. was conducted
                    following the methods described in the &#x0201c;Italian Guidelines for
                    Legionellosis prevention and control&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">
                    19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p>
                <p>Ten millilitres of the sample were first put into a sterile screw-capped Falcon
                    tube, and then, a one-litre sample of water was concentrated by filtration on a
                    0.20&#x02009;&#x003bc;m pore-diameter cellulose membrane filter.</p>
                <p>The membranes were aseptically removed and placed into the sterile screw-capped
                    Falcon tube previously filled with 10&#x02009;ml of water sample collected; the
                    material collected onto the membrane filter was vortex-mixed continuously for
                    2&#x02009;min.</p>
                <p>Ten millilitres of the sample was divided into two aliquots of 5&#x02009;ml each;
                    one aliquot was incubated at 50&#x000b0;C in a water bath for 30 minutes
                    (treated sample) and the second aliquot remained at room temperature
                    (non-treated sample).</p>
                <p>Next, 0.1&#x02009;ml of the treated and non-treated samples was spread on a
                    90&#x02009;mm Petri dish containing GVPC-selective medium (glycine, polymyxin B,
                    vancomycin and cycloheximide). These plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C in a
                    humidified atmosphere with 2.5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Plates were evaluated for a
                    maximum of 14&#x02009;days before reporting them negative.</p>
                <p>Suspected colonies that displayed a distinctive surface with an iridescent and
                    faceted cut glass appearance were counted from each sampling. Gram staining was
                    performed on the suspected colonies; weakly staining, gram-negative bacilli were
                    observable. Suspicious colonies were sub-cultured both onto buffered charcoal
                    yeast extract (BCYE) agar with cysteine and charcoal yeast extract agar (CYE
                    Agar Base &#x02013; Oxoid) for verification.</p>
                <p>These plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere with 2.5%
                    CO<sub>2</sub> for &#x02265;2&#x02009;days.</p>
                <p>The isolated colonies growing only on BCYE, but that did not grow on CYE, were
                    determined to be <italic>Legionella</italic> colonies. Subsequently, these
                    colonies were serotyped by the agglutination <italic>Legionella</italic> Latex
                    Test (Oxoid) that provides separate identification of <italic>L. pneumophila</italic>
                    serogroup 1, <italic>L. pneumophila</italic> serogroups 2&#x02013;14 and other
                    species of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. that have been implicated in human
                    disease: <italic>L. longbeachae</italic> 1 and 2, <italic>L. bozemanii</italic>
                    1 and 2, <italic>L. dumoffii</italic>, <italic>L. gormanii</italic>, <italic>L.
                    jordanis</italic>, <italic>L. micdadei</italic> and <italic>L. anisa.</italic></p>
                <p>According to the Italian Guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>],
                    quantitative evaluation (CFU/L) was performed considering the following items:
                    the count of colonies growth in each plate, the concentration of the original
                    sample and the dilutions successively made.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Water supply on board trains and environmental decontamination procedures</title>
                <p>The water distributed in the toilets of passenger cars, both for the washbasin
                    and for sanitary services, must have, at the time of supply, the characteristics
                    required for human consumption. Because of the characteristics of hydraulic
                    systems on board, these requirements cannot be fully insured, so water is
                    labelled "no drinking".</p>
                <p>Passenger railway cars are fitted with steel or resin tanks in which the total
                    volume of water is variable depending on the type of car (ranging from 200 to
                    1,800 litres).</p>
                <p>The water tanks are located under the car&#x02019;s roof and the water flows into
                    the toilets by gravity.</p>
                <p>Tanks are refilled at stations or through installation maintenance by jet spouts
                    placed on side rails and discharge takes place through a special tap below the
                    wagon.</p>
                <p>When <italic>Legionella</italic> bacterial load was greater than 10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;CFU/L,
                    decontamination procedures were performed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>
                    ,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Decontamination was completed in
                    September 2008 (pre-decontamination step&#x02009;=&#x02009;September
                    2006-September 2008), so October 2008 is considered the beginning of the
                    post-decontamination period.</p>
                <p>The measures of supply reservoir and pipeline decontamination involve chemical
                    de-scaling with 20% acetic acid and hyper-chlorination with 20&#x02009;mg/l for
                    2 hours or 50&#x02009;mg/l for 1 hour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>
                    ,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], followed by washing to reach
                    0.2&#x02009;mg/l of free residual chlorine concentration, or even replacement in
                    limited cases of obvious damage.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Statistical methods</title>
                <p>The prevalence proportion of all positive samples was calculated; the following
                    bacterial load values were adopted to perform a statistical analysis:
                    &#x0003c;100&#x02009;CFU/L, 100&#x02013;999&#x02009;CFU/L,
                    1,000-9,999&#x02009;CFU/L, &#x0003e;10,000&#x02009;CFU/L.</p>
                <p>The unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test was performed to evaluate statistically
                    significant differences between the mean load values before and after the
                    decontamination procedures; statistical significance was set at <italic>p</italic>
                    &#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>The overall number of water samples collected from different trains and analysed from
                September 2006 to January 2011 was 1,245 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).
                Of those, 679 were collected during the pre-decontamination period.</p>
            <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Results of the microbiological analysis performed on the water samples
                        collected</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="left" />
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left">&#x000a0;</th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>Pre-decontamination period</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>Post-decontamination period</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>Total</bold>
                            </th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                                <italic>Number of water samples analysed</italic>
                                <hr />
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">679 (54.538% of total samples analyzed)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">566 (45.462% of total samples analyzed)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1245<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples positive for
                                Legionella</italic> spp.<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">394 (58.027%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">242 (42.756%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">636<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples positive for
                                L. pneumophila</italic> 1<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">220 (55.838%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">177 (73.140%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">397<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples positive for
                                L. pneumophila</italic> 2 -14<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">75 (19.036%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">39 (16.116%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">114<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples positive for
                                L. pneumophila</italic> 1 and 2 -14<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">99 (25.127%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">23 (9.504%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">122<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples positive for
                                Legionella other</italic> species<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0 (0.000%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">3 (1.240%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples with</italic>
                                load values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;100&#x02009;CFU/L<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">69 (17.513%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">14 (5.785%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">83<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples with</italic>
                                load values 100&#x02013;999&#x02009;CFU/L<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">155 (39.340%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">121 (50.000%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">276<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Number of samples with</italic>
                                load values 1,000-9,999 CFU/L<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">138 (35.025%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">85 (35.124%)<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">223<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left"><italic>Number of samples with</italic> load
                                values&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;10,000 CFU/L</td>
                            <td align="left">32 (8.122%)</td>
                            <td align="left">22 (9.091%)</td>
                            <td align="left">54</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>In the pre-decontamination period, 58% of water samples were positive for <italic>
                Legionella</italic> and only <italic>L. pneumophila</italic> was identified; 55.84%
                contained serogroup 1, 19.03% contained serogroups 2&#x02013;14 and 25.13% contained
                both serogroups.</p>
            <p>The mean bacterial load value was 2.14&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;CFU/L;
                17.51% of positive samples had a load value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;100, 39.34%
                ranged from 100 to 999, 35.03% ranged from 1,000 to 9,999 and 8.12%
                were&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10,000&#x02009;CFU/L.</p>
            <p>During the post-decontamination period, 566 water samples were collected and
                analysed: 42.75% were positive for <italic>Legionella</italic> and <italic>Legionella
                pneumophila</italic> was identified in 98.76% of the positive samples; 74.06%
                contained serogroup 1, 16.32% contained serogroups 2&#x02013;14 and 9.62% contained
                both serogroups.</p>
            <p>The mean bacterial load of positive samples in the post-decontamination period was
                1.72&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;CFU/L: 5.79% had a load
                value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;100, 50% were between 100 and 999, 35.12% were
                between 1,000, and 9,999 and 9.09%
                were&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10,000&#x02009;CFU/L.</p>
            <p>The unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test was performed to compare post-decontamination
                results to pre-decontamination levels; there was a statistically significant
                decrease in total bacterial load after January 2009: <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0309
                (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The statistically significant
                decrease in total bacterial load continued until March 2010 (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0097),
                confirming the intervention&#x02019;s effectiveness until approximately one and a
                half years after beginning the decontamination period.</p>
            <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>
                        <bold>Effectiveness of decontamination on</bold>
                        <bold>
                            <italic>Legionella</italic>
                        </bold>
                        <bold>bacterial loading</bold>
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="char" />
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="left" />
                        <col align="left" />
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead valign="top">
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>Month</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="char">
                                <bold>Mean of load value (CFU/l) (post-decontamination period)</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>Mean of bacterial load in natural logarithmic numbers</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>t</bold>
                            </th>
                            <th align="left">
                                <bold>
                                    <italic>p</italic>
                                </bold>
                            </th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="top">
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">October 2008<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">992.2414<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.9000<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.6591<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.2550<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">November 2008<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">583.8235<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.3696<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.1843<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1183<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">December 2008<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">397.0000<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.9839<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.6083<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0541<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">January 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">320.1613<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.7688<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.8698<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0309<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">February 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">295.1282<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.6874<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.1259<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0169<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">March 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">306.3265<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.7247<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.3673<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0091<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">April 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">315.3801<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.7538<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.5402<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0056<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">May 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">295.0256<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">5.6871<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.7428<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0031<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">June 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">417.9909<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.0355<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.7060<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0035<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">July 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">498.4615<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.2115<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.6624<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0039<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">August 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">554.6850<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.3184<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.6735<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0038<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">September 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">592.1561<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.3838<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.6817<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0037<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">October 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">753.6237<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.6249<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.4677<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0069<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">November 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">752.5163<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.6234<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.5500<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0055<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">December 2009<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">748.6751<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.6183<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.6023<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0047<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">January 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">726.0479<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.5876<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.7144<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0034<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">February 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">934.4538<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.8400<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.3195<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0103<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">March 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">962.5000<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">6.8695<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">2.3432<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0097<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">April 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1369.3270<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.2221<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.3341<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0912<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">May 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1314.9530<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.1816<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.4680<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.0712<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">June 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1521.4860<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.3274<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.0917<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1376<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">July 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1482.9550<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.3018<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">1.1885<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1174<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">August 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1707.7110<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.4429<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.7837<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.2167<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">September 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1697.6230<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.4370<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.8044<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.2107<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">October 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1684.2690<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.4291<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.8432<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1996<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">November 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1635.7890<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.3999<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.9556<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.1697<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">December 2010<hr /></td>
                            <td align="char" valign="bottom" char=".">1719.8530<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">7.4500<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.8037<hr /></td>
                            <td align="left" valign="bottom">0.2109<hr /></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left">January 2011</td>
                            <td align="char" char=".">1721.6250</td>
                            <td align="left">7.4510</td>
                            <td align="left">0.8141</td>
                            <td align="left">0.2079</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>[In Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> are reported the results
                        of the unpaired t-tests performed to compare the mean value of the bacterial
                        load in the pre-decontamination period (grand mean: 2142.7840&#x02009;CFU/L
                        &#x02013; 7.6698 in logarithmic value) with the ones of the
                        post-decontamination period].</p>
                </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Several studies describe the frequency of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp.
                contamination in spa pools, natural pools and hotels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">
                7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Cases of LD are also well
                documented among cruise ship passengers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. To date, this is the first study
                concerning the environmental monitoring of <italic>Legionella</italic> on board
                trains.</p>
            <p>This study demonstrates the necessity for periodic evaluation on trains to assess the
                potential contamination of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp., with the aim to drive
                decontamination efforts in the absence of specific guidelines. We hypothesized that
                an environmental surveillance programme, followed by decontamination procedures when
                necessary, would decrease the total bacterial load, thereby protecting the health of
                travellers and workers.</p>
            <p>This study demonstrated a statistically significant decrease in total bacterial load
                after decontamination procedures. The <italic>t</italic>-test indicated a decrease
                in bacterial load since October 2008, with statistical significance from January
                2009 to March 2010, suggesting that a disinfection treatment performed every one and
                a half years could reduce environmental contamination.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this study demonstrated a decrease in <italic>Legionella</italic>-positive
                samples after decontamination procedures: 58% in the pre-decontamination period and
                42.75% in post one were positive for <italic>Legionella.</italic> Although there was
                a decrease in the total <italic>Legionella</italic>-positive samples, we observed an
                increase of <italic>Legionella</italic> serogroup 1 (55.84% pre- vs. 74.06%
                post-decontamination), which is responsible for approximately 70% of <italic>
                Legionella</italic> infections in Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>].
                This increase could have been due to the development of a protective biofilm,
                especially when load values were high. As demonstrated in this study, the
                disinfection treatments were more effective when the bacterial load was lower
                (17.51% of positive samples with a load
                value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;100&#x02009;CFU/L in pre- vs. 5.79% in
                post-decontamination).</p>
            <p>Even if hyper-chlorination of the water is consistently performed, this approach is
                particularly appropriate for the treatment and removal of planktonic cultures of <italic>L.
                pneumophila</italic>, but remains ineffective against sessile communities of the
                bacterium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p>
            <p>This study suggests that the resistance to chlorination of <italic>L. pneumophila</italic>
                serogroup 1 could be due to the biofilm that facilitates a higher tolerance to the
                disinfectant. In fact, we observed limestone deposits in different water tanks in
                which the biofilm could have been developed. Environmental strains could develop a
                resistance mechanism to chlorine-based disinfection treatments, so these
                decontamination procedures are not completely appropriate for removing the bacterium
                from plumbing and tanks. As these procedures do not lead to a definitive solution to
                the problem, we suggest that mechanical cleaning could increase the effectiveness
                and length of chemical decontamination procedures, thereby reducing bacterial load
                values and increasing the amount of time that the water can be considered safe.</p>
            <p>We aimed to highlight that environmental surveillance represents an evidence-based
                approach for evaluating the contamination of the water supply on board trains. This
                work stresses the effectiveness of decontamination and, above all, provides
                information about the required frequency of disinfection procedures to achieve a
                statistically significant decrease in total bacterial load.</p>
            <p>Periodic environmental surveillance could be a useful approach for assessing the risk
                of exposure to <italic>Legionella</italic> bacteria, which still poses a threat to
                public health. <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. are opportunists par excellence and
                are therefore especially dangerous for vulnerable individuals (e.g., older people,
                current tobacco smokers, immune-compromised or immune-suppressed persons, patients
                with chronic degenerative diseases and transplanted people).</p>
            <p>Our purpose is to ensure the safety of the passengers and the workers on board trains
                by defining proper preventive measures to be implemented with an established
                frequency.</p>
            <p>The primary limitation of this study concerns the use of the <italic>t</italic>-test;
                a paired <italic>t</italic>-test was not performed because this study focused on the
                general trend of contamination/decontamination on board trains as opposed to a
                specific sampling site.</p>
            <p>Moreover in this study we analyzed only environmental data because we were given the
                responsibility of doing only the environmental surveillance; in fact, clinical
                surveillance was carried out by other institutions and, up to date, we have no
                information about cases of Legionellosis linked to our environmental data.</p>
            <p>The lengthy time period of the environmental surveillance and the large number of
                water samples collected and analysed represent a point of strength in this study.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="conclusions">
            <title>Conclusions</title>
            <p>Public health programmes should focus on reducing the risk for LD among travellers.</p>
            <p>In addition to cruise ships and ferries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>],
                the routine monitoring of water on board trains must be considered an essential
                measure of primary prevention for guaranteeing water safety and, consequently, to
                avoid cases of LD. For these reasons, the drafting of guidelines for LD prevention
                on public transportation may be necessary to protect the health of travellers and
                workers. According to our experience, it is necessary to pay close attention to
                water quality on board trains, especially after decontamination procedures to
                prevent bacterial colonization.</p>
            <p>Although the eradication of <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. in plumbing and water
                tanks is difficult to achieve, our approach can be considered an evidence-based
                method for assessing and managing <italic>Legionella</italic> infection risk on
                trains.</p>
            <p>The air conditioning plants on board Trenitalia trains are designed to avoid air
                conditioner condensation drip. The particular characteristics of water supply
                facilities on trains, which work by gravity at a low pressure, and the lack of
                showers reduce the possibility of the formation of aerosol, which is potentially
                dangerous for Legionellosis. Nevertheless, Italian Railways have carried out the
                present study in collaboration with Catholic University in Rome and the positive
                results may improve future train sanitation following the practical measures
                described in detail in this article.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Abbreviations</title>
            <p>CFU: Colony forming unit; CFU/L: Colony forming unit/litre.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Competing interests</title>
            <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Authors' contributions</title>
            <p>GQ participated in the design of the study, contributed to draft the manuscript and
                performed the statistical analysis. SV performed the microbiological analysis,
                conceived of the study and helped to draft the manuscript. AMF conceived of the
                study and helped to manage the database and to draft the manuscript. FB performed
                the microbiological analysis. RS performed the microbiological analysis. CT
                performed the microbiological analysis. MDG helped to manage the database and draft
                the manuscript. GC,CC, MA and PDN conceived of the study and participated in its
                design and coordination. EM conceived of the study and participated in its design
                and coordination, allowing the surveillance on board train. WR conceived of the
                study and participated in its design and coordination. PL conceived of the study,
                participated in its design and coordination, carried out the surveillance and helped
                to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Pre-publication history</title>
            <p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p>
            <p>
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                    xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/12/618/prepub">
                    http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/12/618/prepub</ext-link>
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <ref id="B1">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Carratal&#x000e0;</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Garcia-Vidal</surname>
                        <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>An update on Legionella</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <volume>23</volume>
                    <fpage>152</fpage>
                    <lpage>157</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QCO.0b013e328336835b</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20051846</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ricketts</surname>
                        <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Joseph</surname>
                        <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Yadav</surname>
                        <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Travel-associated Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease in Europe in
                        2008. On behalf of the European Working Group for Legionella Infections</article-title>
                    <source>Euro Surveill</source>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <issue>21</issue>
                    <fpage>19578</fpage>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http//www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?Articled=19578">
                        http//www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?Articled=19578</ext-link>.</comment>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519105</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ricketts</surname>
                        <given-names>KD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Joseph</surname>
                        <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>The impact of new guidelines in Europe for the control and
                        prevention of travel-associated Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease. On behalf of
                        the European Working Group for Legionella Infections</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Hyg Environ Health</source>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <volume>209</volume>
                    <fpage>547</fpage>
                    <lpage>552</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2006.05.003</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815095</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Joseph</surname>
                        <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ricketts</surname>
                        <given-names>KD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Yadav</surname>
                        <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Patel</surname>
                        <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <collab>on behalf of the European Working Group for Legionella Infections</collab>
                    <article-title>Travel-associated Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease in Europe in 2009</article-title>
                    <source>Euro Surveill</source>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <issue>41</issue>
                    <fpage>19683</fpage>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?Articled=19683">
                        http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?Articled=19683</ext-link>.</comment>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20961516</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
                    <collab>European Working Group of Legionella Infections</collab>
                    <source>European Guidelines for control and prevention of travel associated
                        Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease</source>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.hpa.org.uk/Topics/InfectiousDisease/InfectionsAZ/LegionnairesDisease/Guidelines/legiEuropeanAdviceandGuidance">
                        http://www.hpa.org.uk/Topics/InfectiousDisease/InfectionsAZ/LegionnairesDisease/Guidelines/legiEuropeanAdviceandGuidance</ext-link>
                        .</comment>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Rota</surname>
                        <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Caporali</surname>
                        <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Giannitelli</surname>
                        <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Mandarino</surname>
                        <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Scaturro</surname>
                        <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ricci</surname>
                        <given-names>ML</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Rapporto annuale sulla Legionellosi in Italia nel 2009</article-title>
                    <source>Not Ist Super Sanit&#x000e0;</source>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <volume>239</volume>
                    <fpage>3</fpage>
                    <lpage>9</lpage>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Huhn</surname>
                        <given-names>GD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Adam</surname>
                        <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ruden</surname>
                        <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Hilliard</surname>
                        <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
                        <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Todd</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Crafts</surname>
                        <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Passaro</surname>
                        <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Dworkin</surname>
                        <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Outbreak of travel-related pontiac fever among hotel guests
                        illustrating the need for better diagnostic tests</article-title>
                    <source>J Travel Med</source>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                    <issue>4</issue>
                    <fpage>173</fpage>
                    <lpage>179</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16086890</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Modi</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Gardner</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Lighton</surname>
                        <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Coetzee</surname>
                        <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Pontiac fever outbreak associated with a spa-pool</article-title>
                    <source>United Kingdom Euro Surveill</source>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <issue>30</issue>
                    <fpage>13</fpage>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Guyard</surname>
                        <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Low</surname>
                        <given-names>DE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Legionella infections and travel associated legionellosis</article-title>
                    <source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <issue>4</issue>
                    <fpage>176</fpage>
                    <lpage>186</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2010.05.006</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21995862</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Jernigan</surname>
                        <given-names>DB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Hofmann</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Cetron</surname>
                        <given-names>MS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Genese</surname>
                        <given-names>CA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Nuorti</surname>
                        <given-names>JP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Fields</surname>
                        <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Benson</surname>
                        <given-names>RF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Carter</surname>
                        <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Edelstein</surname>
                        <given-names>PH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Guerrero</surname>
                        <given-names>IC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Paul</surname>
                        <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Lipman</surname>
                        <given-names>HB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Breiman</surname>
                        <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Outbreak of Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease among cruise ship
                        passengers exposed to a contaminated whirlpool spa</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <issue>3479000</issue>
                    <fpage>494</fpage>
                    <lpage>499</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8596266</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Rowbotham</surname>
                        <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Legionellosis associated with ships: 1977 to 1997</article-title>
                    <source>Commun Dis Public Health</source>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>146</fpage>
                    <lpage>151</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9782626</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Minooee</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Rickman</surname>
                        <given-names>LS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Infectious diseases on cruise ships</article-title>
                    <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <issue>4</issue>
                    <fpage>737</fpage>
                    <lpage>743</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/520426</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10589880</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Cayla</surname>
                        <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Maldonado</surname>
                        <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Gonzales</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Pellicer</surname>
                        <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Ferrer</surname>
                        <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Pelaz</surname>
                        <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Gracia</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Baladron</surname>
                        <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Plasencia</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Legionellosis study group: a small outbreak of
                        Legionnaires&#x02019;s Disease in a cargo ship under repair</article-title>
                    <source>Eur Resp</source>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <volume>176</volume>
                    <fpage>1322</fpage>
                    <lpage>1327</lpage>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Regan</surname>
                        <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>McCann</surname>
                        <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Syed</surname>
                        <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Christie</surname>
                        <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Joseph</surname>
                        <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Colligan</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>McGaffin</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Outbreak of Legionnaires&#x02019; Disease on a cruise ship:
                        lessons for International surveillance and control</article-title>
                    <source>Commun Dis Public Health</source>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>152</fpage>
                    <lpage>156</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12889297</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <collab>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</collab>
                    <article-title>Cruise-ship-associated Legionnaires disease</article-title>
                    <source>Centers Dis Control Prev (CDC)</source>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <volume>54</volume>
                    <issue>45</issue>
                    <fpage>1153</fpage>
                    <lpage>1155</lpage>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Azara</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Piana</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Sotgiu</surname>
                        <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Dettori</surname>
                        <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Deriu</surname>
                        <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Masia</surname>
                        <given-names>MD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Are</surname>
                        <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Maresu</surname>
                        <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Prevalence study of Legionella spp. contamination in ferries and
                        cruise ships</article-title>
                    <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <issue>6</issue>
                    <fpage>100</fpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16620388</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Goutziana</surname>
                        <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Mouchtouri</surname>
                        <given-names>VA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Karanika</surname>
                        <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Kavagias</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Stathakis</surname>
                        <given-names>NE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Gorgoulianis</surname>
                        <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Kremastinou</surname>
                        <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Hadjichristodoulou</surname>
                        <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Legionella species colonization of water distribution systems,
                        pools and air conditioning systems in cruise ships and ferries</article-title>
                    <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <issue>8</issue>
                    <fpage>390</fpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19025638</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Munaf&#x000f2;</surname>
                        <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Accorsi</surname>
                        <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Del Nord</surname>
                        <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Mansi</surname>
                        <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Laurenti</surname>
                        <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Guidelines for the prevention and control of the Legionella spp
                        contamination in the water tanks of railways cars</article-title>
                    <source>Proceedings of the Union International des Services Medicaux des Chemins
                        de Fer (UIMC) Congress</source>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <publisher-name>Brussels</publisher-name>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
                    <collab>Gazzetta Ufficiale n.103 del 5 maggio</collab>
                    <source>Linee guida per la prevenzione e il controllo della Legionellosi</source>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.guritel.it/free-sum/ARTI/2000/05/05/sommario.html">
                        http://www.guritel.it/free-sum/ARTI/2000/05/05/sommario.html</ext-link>.</comment>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
                    <collab>Gazzetta Ufficiale n.29 del 5 febbraio</collab>
                    <source>Linee guida recanti indicazioni ai laboratori con attivit&#x000e0; di
                        diagnosi microbiologica e controllo ambientale della Legionellosi</source>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.guritel.it/free-sum/ARTI/2005/02/05/sommario.html">
                        http://www.guritel.it/free-sum/ARTI/2005/02/05/sommario.html</ext-link>.</comment>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
                    <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
                    <source>Legionella and the prevention of legionellosis</source>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/emerging/legionella.pdf">
                        http://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/emerging/legionella.pdf</ext-link>
                        .</comment>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Cooper</surname>
                        <given-names>IR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Hanlon</surname>
                        <given-names>GW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <article-title>Resistance of Legionella pneumophila serotype 1 biofilms to
                        chlorine-based disinfection</article-title>
                    <source>J Hosp Infect</source>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>152</fpage>
                    <lpage>159</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2009.07.005</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783074</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>